<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Multimodal Functional Connectivity | Wanze Xie</title>
    <link>https://happytudouni.github.io/tags/multimodal-functional-connectivity/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://happytudouni.github.io/tags/multimodal-functional-connectivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Multimodal Functional Connectivity</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://happytudouni.github.io/img/static/img/LABID.jpg</url>
      <title>Multimodal Functional Connectivity</title>
      <link>https://happytudouni.github.io/tags/multimodal-functional-connectivity/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal Network Analysis</title>
      <link>https://happytudouni.github.io/project/multimodal-network-analysis-in-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://happytudouni.github.io/project/multimodal-network-analysis-in-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My colleagues and I are estimating brain network activity in children (infants and toddlers) using both neural and hemodynamic methods and use these estimates to predict neurodevelopmental outcome later in life as quantified by Mullen and WPPSI tests. We expect that the combined brain network connectivity measures calculated using combined electroencephalography (EEG) and functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS) will be more informative than metrics calculated from either modality alone. To accomplish this task, we are using an MRI-based localization scheme (inverse reconstruction) to project both modalities to a common brain space for each individual.  The children in this project had EEG and fNIRS data collected with comparable baseline paradigms in two different sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will compare the functional connectivity from both modalities within the same network(s) and between the same brain ROIs. The brain functional connectivity and network (e.g., graph theory) measures from both metrics will then be associated with adverse experiences (e.g., SES and inflammation) and will be used to predict cognitive outcomes. The predictive power of each modality and class of metrics will be assessed separately and together.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
